## **SUNIL BALIJA**

## **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

Front End Developer with professional experience focused on web design, development, and web services along with Automation Testing. Skilled in using Agile/Scrum testing concepts such as Test-Driven Development (TDD) and Behavior-Driven Development (BDD) with Ruby, Gherkin, JavaScript, and Groovy, and frameworks such as Cucumber, RSpec, Factory Girl, Capybara and Selenium. Additionally, is well versed in RESTful APIs and Web Services, creating SQL queries for the development, JIRA for project management purposes such as storyboard and logging defects, and using continuous integration tools such as Jenkins. Background in Ruby on Rails development and is enthusiastic about putting automation development experience to use on future projects. Furthermore, demonstrates excellent communication and interpersonal skills.

**TECHNICAL SKILLS** 

Operating Systems: Linux, Unix, Mac OS, Windows

Languages: HTML 5, CSS 3, Java, JavaScript (jQuery, React.js), Ruby, Gherkin, SQL,

Python, PL/SQL, Java, XML

Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL (RDBMS), CouchDB, MongoDB (NoSQL)

**Tools:** Angular 6, 8, 10,11, 15, 16 Ionic 4, 5, Selenium, Factory Girl, Capybara,

Selenium, Jenkins, RVM, Git, GitHub, JIRA, Workfront, TestNG, Tomcat Server, Rational Rose, Jasmine, Puppet, Varnish, Apache, Docker,

Passenger, Nginx, Unicorn

Related Skills: Agile/Scrum, Kanban, TDD, BDD, Automation Testing, Regression Testing,

System Testing, Unite Testing, Manual Testing, RSpec, Cucumber

Framework, RESTful APIs, Web Services, SOAP, LaTeX, JSON, XML Schemas,

J2EE, JSP, Servlets

**EXPERIENCE** 

Kforce/Home Depot Nov-2021 - Present

Front End Developer

- Building new angular applications by using Angular 16, Java 8.
- Migrating internal applications from Angular JS to latest versions of Angular (Angular 16) along with Java upgrade
- Hands on experience with Java services and integrating the Service with Client.
- Good Hands-on experience on designing and implementation of multi-tier applications using web0based technologies like Spring MVC and Spring boot.
- Writing Unit tests cases by using Jest and covering service scenarios.
- Work with NGRX and RXJS for store and state management.
- High development knowledge of ag grid for table creation and styling them according to the client requirement.
- High level usage of SCSS and material styling guide for challenging styling task.
- Update of Style guide libraries for applications within the Home Depot and resolve any issues by updating the security issues.
- Create Java Services and maintain and deploy updates frequently.
- Maintain and give support with the live applications and resolving any issues.

**Environment:** Agile Scrum, Angular16, Angular JS, Scss, HTML, NgRx, Redux, Java 11, JavaScript, RESTful, Git, Jenkins, JIRA, JIRA Workspace, Jest, Java 8

RBFCU Mar 2019 – Nov-2021

Front End Developer

San Antonio, Tx

- Worked with Angular 7, 8 and Ionic as the front-end developer for developing Mobile application and web site.
- Writing Unit tests and Integration tests by using Just, Jasmine and Cucumber.
- Good experience in State Management and Interactions of data by using NgRx.
- Deploying new changes to production and releasing new versions every week.
- Creating stories for new Modules. And working assigning task to team to accomplish sprint goals.
- Actively participating in code reviews for improving code quality.
- Upgrading Ionic versions with full testing the new behaviors, working with Ionic team for submitting defects and following them through Forums.

**Environment:** Agile Scrum, Angular7, Ionic3, Scss, HTML, NgRx, Redex, Java, JavaScript, RESTful, Git, Jenkins, JIRA, Workfront, Jest

## **CAS (Chemical Abstract Solutions)**

Sep 2017 - Jan 2019

Front End Developer

Columbus, OH

- Worked with Angular 5 as the front-end framework and Ruby, Scala as backend.
- Solid understanding of front-end web development and design using HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, TypeScript, Bootstrap, ngx-bootstrap and other Node packages
- Had a great experience in upgrading the ruby version from the 2.2.10 to 2.6.0 and successfully faced the difficulties and problems and resolved them.
- Develop using Test-Driven-Development with using libraries like Test Bed to unit test and validate development release.
- Participating in all the business meetings for writing the business logics with product owners per the requirement using ruby.
- Redesigned user Interface for the website using the Ruby, Angular, Bootstrap, Ajax for View.
- Experience in developing the Ruby Germs and Ruby core and ruby standard Libraries.
- Implemented rest endpoints for new features in line with business requirements.
- Strong understanding of agile principles, using pair programming to deliver features.
- Used ruby Cucumber for testing the end-to-end flow scenarios.
- Proficient in debugging and performance testing of Restful APIs
- Set up Web API Endpoints to consume data by various Web applications.
- Used Groovy and Spock framework for writing Behavior Driven tests for Ruby implementations.

**Environment:** Agile Scrum, Angular 5, 8,10, CSS, HTML, Ruby 2.2, 2.6, Cucumber, Java, Scala, Spark, JavaScript, RESTful, Git, Jenkins, JIRA.

PAYPAL Aug 2016 – Sep 2017

Front End Developer

- Developed and tested many features in an Agile environment using Ruby on Rails, HTML5, CSS, JavaScript, Bootstrap, and RSpec.
- Composed Cucumber and RSpec tests in the application and coded in JavaScript for page usefulness and popup screens.
- Developed and Tested features using Ruby on Rails and Cucumber.
- User Interface for a website with ERB, JQuery, RJS, Ruby, Ajax for View, Controller, Model in Ruby on Rails Framework on Mac OS X Operating System.
- Transitioned software development efforts to a Test-Driven Development (TDD) process, which brought QA testing in on the front-end of the development cycle for gains in code quality, software functionality, and programmer productivity.
- Involved in automation using Java, Selenium WebDriver, TestNG, Cucumber, and Apache POI.

- Extensive experience in developing Ruby Gems and scripting using Ruby Core and Ruby Standard Libraries.
- Used Rails, AJAX, JSON, CSS and JQUERY to design the front end of the application.
- The primary application is a JavaScript SPA using modular construction, the framework, AMD loader, and JSON Schema to front a RESTful API built with SQL.
- Performed analysis, maintenance, and build-out the web site, a high-volume AWS-hosted multiserver application that provides listing search to the public.
- Used scaffolding to design and develop the controller and the view part of the system.
- Provided validations and scope for many models present in the database and created.

**Environment:** Agile Scrum, Ruby 2.1, Rails 4.2, MongoDB, Cucumber, RSpec, Unicorn, HTML5, CSS3, SOAP, AJAX, jQuery, JavaScript, RESTful, Git

Blooms Solution Inc. Sep

**2013 –July 2015** *Front End Engineer* 

- Developed JavaBeans to ease the implementation and deployment of application components.
- Worked in the design and development phases of the application to create and design technical specification documents on the Linux environment, developed the Web application using Ruby on Rails.
- Formulated Use Cases for each business requirement and normalized the use cases to suit the requirements.
- Pro-actively worked upon upload care-ruby gem and ng-upload care libraries to store images, videos and retrieve data from social RESTful APIs.

**Environment:** Ruby, Rails, Java, J2EE, JSP, Servlets, HTML, XML, JavaScript, Struts 1.1, PL/SQL, Tomcat Server, Rational Rose

## **EDUCATION**

Masters in IT

**University of Cumberland (2021)** 

Master's in Computer Science

**University of Central Missouri (2016)** 

Bachelor's in Computer Science and Engineering

Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University (2012)